<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="ch0016s0004" role="Heading">
   <sect1info>
      <risinfo>
         <risprev>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0003</risprev>
         <riscurrent>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0004</riscurrent>
         <risnext>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0005</risnext>
         <booktitle>Diagnostic Interviewing</booktitle>
         <isbn>9781071643624</isbn>
         <chapternumber>16</chapternumber>
         <chapterid>ch0016</chapterid>
         <chaptertitle>14. Sexual Dysfunctions, Gender Dysphoria, and Paraphilic Disorders</chaptertitle>
         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <personname>
                  <firstname>Daniel L.</firstname>
                  <surname>Segal</surname>
               </personname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <publisher>
            <publishername>Springer US</publishername>
         </publisher>
         <pubdate>2025</pubdate>
      </risinfo>
      <primaryauthor>
         <personname>
            <firstname>Daniel L.</firstname>
            <surname>Segal</surname>
         </personname>
      </primaryauthor>
   </sect1info>
   <title>Case Illustrations</title>
   <sect2 id="ch0016s0004s01" role="Heading">
      <title>Case 1</title>
      <para role="Para">Kelly (early 20s) was referred to sex therapy by her general practitioner for “painful sex.” Her spouse of 3 years (David, also in his 20s) attended the sex therapy sessions. Kelly and David had abstained from sexual intercourse until their wedding night in keeping with their religious beliefs. In David’s words, “the wedding night was a disaster.” Kelly appeared very nervous and when they tried to have intercourse; she winced and complained of pain when he attempted vaginal penetration. The couple continued their attempts over the next few months and, although penetration eventually became possible, it remained intensely painful for Kelly. She also reported discomfort with tampon insertion, although of lower intensity. They had settled into a pattern of sexual interactions characterized by David’s entreaties to have sex, Kelly’s increasingly anxious attempts to avoid it, and the occasional sexual interaction (about once per month) that was painful for Kelly and unsatisfying for both. They rarely<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>rarely</primary>
         </indexterm> discussed the problem. Kelly reported experiencing sexual desire and arousal during nonpainful sexual<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>sexual</primary>
         </indexterm> activities, but her desire/arousal plummeted when she anticipated or experienced the pain. In terms of their past, both reported supportive families and generally happy childhoods, with no history of physical or sexual abuse. They had no mental health concerns. David reported no sexual concerns, and they both reported a strong and satisfying nonsexual relationship.</para>
      <para role="Para">Areas targeted with psychometric measures were sexual dysfunction, pain-related experiences, and relationship adjustment. Consistent with the information obtained during the clinical interview, FSFI scores supported frequent pain experiences during insertional sexual activity for Kelly and the IIEF did not<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>not</primary>
         </indexterm>reveal evidence of sexual dysfunction in David. A pain scale revealed high pain intensity scores, and her scores on measures of pain catastrophizing and anxiety were very high. The DAS confirmed their report of having a satisfying relationship outside of sexual activity. A referral was made to a gynecologist and a pelvic floor physical therapist with expertise in genitopelvic pain; results were consistent with a diagnosis of provoked vestibulodynia (PVD)<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>provoked vestibulodynia (PVD)</primary>
         </indexterm>, a common cause of genitopelvic pain, with considerable hypertonicity (tightness) of the pelvic floor musculature. The findings from this assessment were used to design a multidisciplinary treatment plan<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>plan</primary>
         </indexterm> that simultaneously targeted all problem areas: genitopelvic pain; feelings of guilt related to, and communication about, sex; hypertonicity; and pain catastrophizing and anxiety.</para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="ch0016s0004s02" role="Heading">
      <title>Case 2</title>
      <para role="Para">Sarah, a 28-year-old trans woman,woman,<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>woman,</primary>
         </indexterm> was referred to sex therapy by her family doctor to obtain a letter for hormone therapy as this step was the next one in her physical transition to a feminine body. Sarah was designated male at birth, but since early childhood (3–4 years of age) recalled feeling distressed about “being a boy,” the stereotypical male toys that she was expected to play with, and the masculine clothing she was expected to wear. She identified as a girl since the age of 5. In her early school years, she avoided sports and all forms of rough-and-tumble play, played only with girls (and typically feminine toys), preferred to wear her hair long, and wore feminine clothing. When asked what she wanted to be “when she grew up,” Sarah would often respond “a woman.” Although she was often bullied by other children (typically boys), her parents, most other family members, and friends (girls) never questioned her choices. As Sarah approached puberty, she noted a sharp increase in distress (severe level) given the more obvious masculine changes that were occurring in her body, especially the<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>the</primary>
         </indexterm> growth of facial hair, the development of a masculine body contour, and the deepening of her voice. Sarah identified as lesbian, and dated several<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>several</primary>
         </indexterm>partners throughout high school and beyond, eventually marrying her current partner, Samantha, at the age of 25. Sarah was always open about her gender with her partners, and Samantha was described as supportive of any changes that Sarah opted for in terms of her journey as a woman. Sarah dressed femininely, wore makeup and nail polish, and was working with a voice coach to raise her pitch. She also wore a padded bra to feel feminine. She was “out” in the trans community as well as with all close individuals in her social network, and she felt that she was ready to take the next step in terms of her physical transition (hormone therapy). Her distress level in terms of her physical body and being “misread” by others as male/man was moderate to high. She expressed realistic expectations in terms of the changes<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>changes</primary>
         </indexterm> that hormone therapy entailed, she understood the risks and benefits of the treatment, and she recognized the reproductive implications of the treatment. She was not interested in surgery at this time.</para>
      <para role="Para">Upon examining her responses to the GIGDQ, Sarah’s gender identity was that of a woman, and her dysphoria was moderate to high. Her scores on anxiety and depression screening tools were in the moderate range. A letter detailing the diagnosis of GD and including the information required by WPATH was sent to a trans-friendly physician at a local clinic to support Sarah’s request for hormone therapy. In addition, Sarah was given a referral to<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>to</primary>
         </indexterm>a trans-friendly mental healthcare<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>healthcare</primary>
         </indexterm> professional to develop coping strategies for her depression and anxiety.</para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="ch0016s0004s03" role="Heading">
      <title>Case 3</title>
      <para role="Para">John (age 56) was convicted of breaching a court order prohibiting contact with children. He babysat a 6-year-old boy who disclosed he had been touched inappropriately on his bottom by John. John had 10 prior sentencing dates over 30 years for a range of offenses; five of these were for sexual offenses. All involved boys aged 7–15. John was raised in an intact family by prosocial parents. However, he said his brother bullied him, which contributed to him acting out in school where his peers ostracized him. Behavioral problems emerged in elementary school and many<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>many</primary>
         </indexterm> suspensions resulted. He was expelled in Grade 10, which ended his formal education. Throughout his adult years, John continued to struggle to make friends but enjoyed the support of his parents. He spent most of his free time alone and at home, which he preferred. John reported having been sexually abused by an adult male neighbor over a period of a few months when he was 7 years old. According to John, he did not see this experience as harmful. This abuse ended when the neighbor moved away. John recalled that he always had a “healthy” sex drive and that he often used sexual fantasy or masturbation to cope with his loneliness and sadness. John had never been in a cohabiting relationship with an age-appropriate partner but expressed that he would like to be; he described not knowing how to approach other adults and feeling overwhelmed by the thought of dating. VR and phallometric testing indicated equivalent responses<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>responses</primary>
         </indexterm> to both pubescent and<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>and</primary>
         </indexterm> pre-pubescent boys, a secondary but significant response to consenting men, and a negligible response to girls and women. He described being sexually attracted to men and admitted to an interest in boys aged 14–16. The results of the interview and testing were consistent with the diagnosis of Pedophilic Disorder.</para>
      <para role="Para">John participated in a treatment program in 2018 where few gains were made. He was described as being unreceptive to feedback and steadfast in asserting his victims “accepted and enjoyed” the abuse. He repeated this belief in the current assessment and stressed that he never pressured them and referred at times to having had a “relationship” with them. In regard to his current breach, John described it was “no big deal.” He denied touching the boy and portrayed his contact with the youth as a benign attempt to help a neighbor who required child care at short notice. He had no insight into his role in engineering these circumstances or the people who gave him access to his victims, and he portrayed his victims as the initiators of the sexual activity.</para>
      <para role="Para">John’s PCL-R score<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>score</primary>
         </indexterm> was below the criterion for designation as a psychopath. John’s scores on the Static-99R and Stable-2007 were consistent with a very strong risk of reoffending. On the Stable-2007, John’s results indicated treatment targets aimed at improving his deficits in forming and maintaining adult<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>adult</primary>
         </indexterm> relationships, emotional identification with children, general social rejection, sexualized coping, deviant sexual preference, and problems in cooperating with supervision. A high-intensity sex offender program<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>program</primary>
         </indexterm> was recommended.</para>
   </sect2>
</sect1>