<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="ch0016s0009">
   <sect1info>
      <risinfo>
         <risprev>sect1.9781071643624.</risprev>
         <riscurrent>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0009</riscurrent>
         <risnext>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0001</risnext>
         <booktitle>Diagnostic Interviewing</booktitle>
         <isbn>9781071643624</isbn>
         <chapternumber>16</chapternumber>
         <chapterid>ch0016</chapterid>
         <chaptertitle>14. Sexual Dysfunctions, Gender Dysphoria, and Paraphilic Disorders</chaptertitle>
         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <personname>
                  <firstname>Daniel L.</firstname>
                  <surname>Segal</surname>
               </personname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <publisher>
            <publishername>Springer US</publishername>
         </publisher>
         <pubdate>2025</pubdate>
      </risinfo>
      <primaryauthor>
         <personname>
            <firstname>Daniel L.</firstname>
            <surname>Segal</surname>
         </personname>
      </primaryauthor>
   </sect1info>
   <title>14. Sexual Dysfunctions, Gender Dysphoria, and Paraphilic Disorders</title>
   <para>D. L. Segal<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (ed.)</emphasis>
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">Diagnostic Interviewing</emphasis>
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-0716-4362-4_14">https://doi. org/10.1007/978-1-0716-4362-4_14</ulink>
      <emphasis role="AuthorName">Caroline F. Pukall</emphasis>
      <superscript>1 <emphasis>ContactOf Author 1</emphasis>
      </superscript> and <emphasis role="AuthorName">Katherine Sutton</emphasis>
      <superscript>2</superscript>(1)(2)Caroline F. Pukall Email:</para>
   <para>caroline. pukall@queensu. ca Sexual dysfunctions Gender dysphoria Paraphilic disorders Assessment Interviewing</para>
   <para role="Para">This chapter focuses<indexterm significance="normal">
         <primary>focuses</primary>
      </indexterm> on three different categories of disorders related to sexual function and pleasure, gender, and distressing or harmful sexual behavior as defined by the DSM-5-TR (American Psychiatric Association, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
         <phrase>2022</phrase>
      </emphasis>): sexual dysfunctions, gender dysphoria, and paraphilic disorders. In general, sexual dysfunctions are conditions that affect one’s ability to function sexually or to experience sexual pleasure; gender dysphoria is a condition in which distress is experienced due to an incongruency between a person’s <emphasis>experienced</emphasis> gender/sex<superscript>1</superscript>(i. e., the internal, psychological experience of a person’s gender/sex) (van Anders,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
         <phrase>2015</phrase>
      </emphasis>) and their <emphasis>assigned</emphasis>gender/sex (i. e., how their gender/sex is perceived by others); and paraphilic disorders are characterized by atypical, intense, and persistent sexual interests that cause distress or harm (or risk of harm). Typically, clinicians working in the area of sex therapy or sexual medicine will see clients with sexual dysfunctions and/or gender dysphoria, whereas clinicians who specialize in forensic psychology will see clients with paraphilic disorders given that these disorders often entail legal consequences.<footnote id="ch0016s0009fn0001">
         <para>Footnotes</para>
         <para>
            <emphasis role="FootnoteNumber">
               <phrase>1</phrase>
            </emphasis>The term “gender/sex” was coined by Dr. Sari van Anders to capture the wholeness of people and their identities in relation to phenomena that cannot be attributed solely to gender or sex. </para>
      </footnote>
   </para>
</sect1>