<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="ch0016s0008" role="Heading">
   <sect1info>
      <risinfo>
         <risprev>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0007</risprev>
         <riscurrent>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0008</riscurrent>
         <risnext>sect1.9781071643624.</risnext>
         <booktitle>Diagnostic Interviewing</booktitle>
         <isbn>9781071643624</isbn>
         <chapternumber>16</chapternumber>
         <chapterid>ch0016</chapterid>
         <chaptertitle>14. Sexual Dysfunctions, Gender Dysphoria, and Paraphilic Disorders</chaptertitle>
         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <personname>
                  <firstname>Daniel L.</firstname>
                  <surname>Segal</surname>
               </personname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <publisher>
            <publishername>Springer US</publishername>
         </publisher>
         <pubdate>2025</pubdate>
      </risinfo>
      <primaryauthor>
         <personname>
            <firstname>Daniel L.</firstname>
            <surname>Segal</surname>
         </personname>
      </primaryauthor>
   </sect1info>
   <title>Summary</title>
   <para role="Para">There are a number of disorders related to sexuality, gender, and paraphilias, and each must be carefully assessed and characterized. At a minimum, a single question about any sexual concern is necessary to potentially raise an issue that the patient may want to address but feels too embarrassed to spontaneously report.</para>
   <sidebar id="ch0016s0008ad01">
      <para/>
   </sidebar>
   <bibliography id="ch0016s0008bib0078">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib01">Abel, G. G., Huffman, J., Warberg, B., &amp; Holland, C. L. (1998). Visual reaction time and plethysmography as measures of sexual interest in child molesters. Sexual Abuse: A Journal of Research and Treatment, 10, 81–95. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib02">Akerman, G., &amp; Beech, A. R. (2012). A systematic review of measures of deviant sexual interest and arousal. Psychiatry, Psychology and Law, 19(1), 118–143. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib03">Alderson, K. G. (2012). Counseling LGBTI clients. Sage.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib04">Amelung, T., Konrad, A., Beier, K. M., &amp; Lehmann, R. J. (2024). The viewing reaction time as a diagnostic tool of pedohebephilia in the Dunkelfeld. Archives of Sexual Behavior, 53(1), 25–42. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib05">American Psychiatric Association. (2022). Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders (5th ed.). American Psychiatric Association.Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib06">Andrews, D. A., &amp; Wormith, J. S. (1984). The criminal sentiments scale. Ministry of Correctional Services of Canada.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib07">Association for the Treatment of Sexual Abusers. (2014). ATSA practice guidelines for assessment, treatment interventions, and management strategies for male adult sexual abusers. ATSA.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib08">Bauer, G., Churchill, S., Ducharme, J., Feder, S., Gillis, L., Gotovac, S., Holmes, C., Lawson, M., Metzger, D., Saewyc, E., Speechley, K., &amp; Temple, J. (2021). Trans youth CAN! Gender distress scale (TYC-GDS). Research Team.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib09">Bauer, G. R., Scheim, A. I., Pyne, J., Travers, R., &amp; Hammond, R. (2015). Intervenable factors associated with suicide risk in transgender persons: a respondent driven sampling study in Ontario, Canada. BMC Public Health, 15, 525. CrossrefPubMedPubMedCentral</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib10">Ben-Porath, Y. S. (2012). Addressing challenges to MMPI-2-RF-based testimony: Questions and answers. Archives of Clinical Neuropsychology, 27(7), 691–705. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib11">Ben-Porath, Y. S., &amp; Tellegen, A. (2020). MMPI-3 manual for administration, scoring, and interpretation. Pearson.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib12">Boehmer, U., Timm, A., Ozonoff, A., &amp; Potter, J. (2012). Applying the female sexual functioning index to sexual minority women. Journal of Women’s Health, 21(4), 401–409. CrossrefPubMedPubMedCentral</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib13">Bonta, J., &amp; Andrews, D. A. (2017). The psychology of criminal conduct (6th ed.). Routledge.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib14">Brankley, A. E., Babchishin, K. M., &amp; Hanson, R. K. (2021). STABLE-2007 demonstrates predictive and incremental validity in assessing risk-relevant propensities for sexual offending: A meta-analysis. Sexual Abuse, 33(1), 34–62. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib15">Briken, P., Fedoroff, J. P., &amp; Bradford, J. W. (2014). Why can’t pedophilic disorder remit? Archives of Sexual Behavior, 43, 1237–1239. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib16">Byne, W., Karasic, D. H., Coleman, E., Eyler, A. E., Kidd, J. D., Meyer-Bahlburg, H. F., Pleak, R. R., &amp; Pula, J. (2018). Gender dysphoria in adults: An overview and primer for psychiatrists. Transgender Health, 3(1), 57–70. CrossrefPubMedPubMedCentral</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib17">Coleman, E., Radix, A. E., Bouman, W. P., Brown, G. R., de Vries, A. L. C., Deutsch, M. B., Ettner, R., Fraser, L., Goodman, M., Green, J., Hancock, A. B., Johnson, T. W., Karasic, D. H., Knudson, G. A., Leibowitz, S. F., Meyer-Bahlburg, H. F., Monstrey, S. J., Motmans, J., Nahata, L., &amp; Arcelus, J. (2022). Standards of care for the health of transgender and gender diverse people, version 8. International Journal of Transgender Health, 23(Suppl 1), S1–S259. CrossrefPubMedPubMedCentral</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib18">Cortoni, F. (2018). Women who sexually abuse: Assessment, treatment &amp; management. Safer Society Press.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib19">Coyne, K., Mandalia, S., McCullough, S., Catalan, J., Noestlinger, C., Colebunders, R., &amp; Asboe, D. (2010). The International Index of Erectile Function: Development of an adapted tool for use in HIV-positive men who have sex with men. The Journal of Sexual Medicine, 7(2), 769–774. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib20">Dargie, E. E., Holden, R., &amp; Pukall, C. F. (2016). The vulvar pain assessment questionnaire inventory. Pain, 157, 2672–2686. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib21">Dawson, S. J., Bannerman, B. A., &amp; Lalumière, M. L. (2016). Paraphilic interests: An examination of sex differences in a non-clinical sample. Sexual Abuse: A Journal of Research and Treatment, 28(1), 20–45. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib22">Derogatis, L. R., Rosen, R., Leiblum, S., Burnett, A., &amp; Heiman, J. (2002). The female sexual distress scale (FSDS): Initial validation of a standardized scale for assessment of sexually related personal distress in women. Journal of Sex &amp; Marital Therapy, 28(4), 317–330. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib23">Duwe, G. (2019). Better practices in the development and validation of recidivism risk assessments: The Minnesota Sex Offender Screening Tool-4. Criminal Justice Policy Review, 30(4), 538–564. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib24">Epperson, D. L., Kaul, J. D., &amp; Huot, S. J. (1995). Predicting risk of recidivism for incarcerated sex offenders: Updated development on the Sex Offender Screening Tool (SOST). Paper presented at the 14th annual conference of the Association for the Treatment of Sexual Abusers, New Orleans, LA.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib25">Graham, C. A., Sanders, S. A., Milhausen, R. R., &amp; McBride, K. R. (2004). Turning on and turning off: A focus group study of the factors that affect women’s sexual arousal. Archives of Sexual Behavior, 33(6), 527–538. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib26">Haag, A. M., Boyes, A., Cheng, J., MacNeil, A., &amp; Wirove, R. (2016). An introduction to the issues of cross-cultural assessment inspired by Ewert v Canada. Journal of Threat Assessment and Management, 3(2), 65–75. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib27">Hall, K. S., &amp; Graham, C. A. (Eds.). (2013). The cultural context of sexual pleasure and problems: Psychotherapy with diverse clients. Routledge.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib28">Hanson, R. K., Harris, A. J., Letourneau, E., Helmus, L. M., &amp; Thornton, D. (2018). Reductions in risk based on time offense-free in the community: Once a sexual offender, not always a sexual offender. Psychology, Public Policy, and Law, 24(1), 48. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib29">Assessing the risk of sexual offenders on community supervision: The dynamic supervision project (user report, corrections research)http://​www.​publicsafety.​gc.​ca/​cnt/​rsrcs/​pblctns/​ssssng-rsk-sxl-ffndrs/​index-eng.​aspx</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib30">Hanson, R. K., &amp; Thornton, D. (2000). Improving risk assessments for sex offenders: A comparison of three actuarial scales. Law and Human Behavior, 24(1), 119–136. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib31">Hardy, K. V., &amp; Laszloffy, T. A. (2002). Couple therapy using a multicultural perspective. In A. S. Gurman &amp; N. S. Jacobson (Eds.), Clinical handbook of couple therapy (3rd ed., pp. 569–593). Guilford.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib32">Hare, R. D. (2003). Manual for the revised psychopathy checklist (2nd ed.). Multi-Health Systems.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib33">Harris, A. J. R., &amp; Hanson, R. K. (2010). Clinical, actuarial, and dynamic risk assessment of sexual offenders: Why do things keep changing? Journal of Sexual Aggression, 16, 296–310. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib34">Healy, D., Bahrick, A., Bak, M., Barbato, A., Salvatore Calabrò, R., Chuback, B. M., Cosci, F., Csoka, A. B., D’Avanzo, B., Diviccaro, S., Giatti, S., Goldstein, I., Graf, S., Hellstrom, W. J. G., Irwig, M. S., Jannini, E. A., Janssen, P. K. C., Khera, M., Kumar, M. T., &amp; Waraich, A. (2022). Diagnostic criteria for enduring sexual dysfunction after treatment with antidepressants, finasteride and isotretinoin. International Journal of Risk &amp; Safety in Medicine, 33(1), 65–76. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib35">Helmus, L. M., Kelley, S. M., Frazier, A., Fernandez, Y. M., Lee, S. C., Rettenberger, M., &amp; Boccaccini, M. T. (2022). Static-99R: Strengths, limitations, predictive accuracy meta-analysis, and legal admissibility review. Psychology, Public Policy, and Law, 28(3), 307–331. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib36">Hopkins, T. A., Brawner, C. A., Meyer, M., Zawilinski, L., Carnes, P. J., &amp; Green, B. A. (2016). MMPI-2 Correlates of sadomasochism in a sexual addiction sample: Contrasting and men and women. Sexual Addiction &amp; Compulsivity, 23(1), 114–140. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib37">Janssen, E., McBride, K., Yarber, W., Hill, B. J., &amp; Butler, S. M. (2008). Factors that influence sexual arousal in men: A focus group study. Archives of Sexual Behavior, 37(2), 252–265. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib38">Joyal, C. C., &amp; Carpentier. (2017). The prevalence of paraphilic interests and behaviors in the general population: A provincial survey. Journal of Sex Research, 54(2), 161–171. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib39">Langevin, R., &amp; Paitich, D. (2002). Clarke sexual history questionnaire for males-revised. Technical manual. Multi-Health Systems.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib40">Laws, D. R., Hanson, R. K., Osborn, C. A., &amp; Greenbaum, P. E. (2000). Classification of child molesters by plethysmographic assessment of sexual arousal and a self-report measure of sexual preference. Journal of Interpersonal Violence, 15, 1297–1312. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib41">Levine, S. B., Risen, C. B., &amp; Althof, A. E. (2016). Handbook of clinical sexuality for mental health professionals (3rd ed.). Taylor &amp; Francis.Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib42"/>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib43">Annals of Plastic Surgery, 86https://​doi.​org/​10.​1097/​SAP.​0000000000002351​CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib44">McCabe, M. P., Sharlip, I. D., Lewis, R., Atalla, E., Balon, R., Fisher, A. D., &amp; Segraves, R. T. (2016). Incidence and prevalence of sexual dysfunction in women and men: A consensus statement from the Fourth International Consultation on Sexual Medicine 2015. The Journal of Sexual Medicine, 13(2), 144–152. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib45">McGuire, J. K., Berg, D., Catalpa, J. M., Morrow, Q. J., Fish, J. N., Nic Rider, G., Steensma, T., Cohen-Kettenis, P. T., &amp; Spencer, K. (2020). Utrecht gender dysphoria scale - gender spectrum (UGDS-GS): Construct validity among transgender, nonbinary, and LGBQ samples. International Journal of Transgender Health, 21(2), 194–208. CrossrefPubMedPubMedCentral</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib46">McPhail, I. V., Hermann, C. A., Fernane, S., Fernandez, Y. M., Nunes, K. L., &amp; Cantor, J. M. (2019). Validity in phallometric testing for sexual interests in children: A meta-analytic review. Assessment, 26(3), 535–551. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib47">Milhausen, R. R., Sakaluk, J. K., Fisher, T. D., Davis, C. M., &amp; Yarber, W. L. (2020). The handbook of sexuality related measures (4th ed.). Routledge.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib48">Multidimensional Inventory of Development, Sex, and Aggression (MIDSA). (2011). MIDSA clinical manual (3rd ed.). Augur Enterprises.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib49">Murrie, D. C., Boccaccini, M. T., Caperton, J., &amp; Rufino, K. (2012). Field validity of the Psychopathy Checklist–Revised in sex offender risk assessment. Psychological Assessment, 24(2), 524–529. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib50">Psychological Assessment, 24https://​doi.​org/​10.​1037/​a 0026015 CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib51">Nichols, H. R., &amp; Molinder, I. (1984). Multiphasic sex inventory manual. Nichols and Molinder Assessments.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib52">Olver, M. E., Mundt, J. C., Thornton, D., Beggs Christofferson, S. M., Kingston, D. A., Sowden, J. N., Nicholaichuk, T. P., Gordon, A., &amp; Wong, S. C. P. (2018). Using the violence risk scale-sexual offense version in sexual violence risk assessments: Updated risk categories and recidivism estimates from a multisite sample of treated sexual offenders. Psychological Assessment, 30(7), 941–955. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib53">Olver, M. E., Wong, S. C. P., Nicholaichuk, T., &amp; Gordon, A. (2007). The validity and reliability of the violence risk scale-sexual offender version: Assessing sex offender risk and evaluating therapeutic change. Psychological Assessment, 19, 318–329. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib54">Psychological Assessment, 19https://​doi.​org/​10.​1037/​1040-3590.​19.​3.​318 CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib55">Phenix, A., Fernandez, Y., Harris, A. J. R., Helmus, M., Hanson, R. K., &amp; Thornton, D. (2016). Static-99R coding rules: Revised—2016.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib56">Pukall, C. F., &amp; Bergeron, S. (2021). Sexual dysfunctions. In L. G. Castonguay, T. F. Oltmanns, &amp; A. Lott (Eds.), Psychopathology: From science to clinical practice (2nd ed., pp. 369–397). Guilford Press.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib57">Quinsey, V. L., Harris, G. T., Rice, M. E., &amp; Cormier, C. A. (2006). Violent offenders: Appraising and managing risk (2nd ed.). American Psychological Association.Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib58">Rice, M. E., Harris, G. T., &amp; Lang, C. (2013). Validation of and revision to the VRAG and SORAG: The violence risk appraisal guide-revised (VRAG-R). Psychological Assessment, 25, 951–965. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib59">Rosen, R., Brown, C., Heiman, J., Leiblum, S., Meston, C., Shabsigh, R., Ferguson, D., &amp; D’Agostino, R. (2000). The female sexual function index (FSFI): A multidimensional self-report instrument for the assessment of female sexual function. Journal of Sex &amp; Marital Therapy, 26(2), 191–208. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib60">Rosen, R. C., Riley, A., Wagner, G., Osterloh, I. H., Kirkpatrick, J., &amp; Mishra, A. (1997). The international index of erectile function (IIEF): A multidimensional scale for assessment of erectile dysfunction. Urology, 49(6), 822–830. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib61">Santos-Iglesias, P., Mohamed, B., Danko, A., &amp; Walker, L. M. (2018). Psychometric validation of the female sexual distress scale in male samples. Archives of Sexual Behavior, 47(6), 1733–1743. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib62">Schmidt, A. F., Babchishin, K. M., &amp; Lehmann, R. J. B. (2017). A meta-analysis of viewing time measures of sexual interest in children. Archives of Sexual Behavior, 46(1), 287–300. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib63">Seto, M. C. (2018). Pedophilia and sexual offending against children: Theory, assessment, and intervention (2nd ed.). American Psychological Association.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib64">Seto, M. C., Kingston, D. A., &amp; Bourget, D. (2014). Assessment of the paraphilias. The Psychiatric Clinics of North America, 37(2), 149–161. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib65">Sills, T., Wunderlich, G., Pyke, R., Segraves, R. T., Leiblum, S., Clayton, A., &amp; Evans, K. (2005). The sexual interest and desire inventory-female (SIDI-F): Item response analyses of data from women diagnosed with hypoactive sexual desire disorder. The Journal of Sexual Medicine, 2(6), 801–818. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib66">Simourd, D. J. (1997). The criminal sentiments scale-modified and pride in delinquency scale: Psychometric properties and construct validity of two measures of criminal attitudes. Criminal Justice and Behavior, 24(1), 52–70. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib67">Spanier, G. B. (1976). Measuring dyadic adjustment: New scales for assessing the quality of marriage and similar dyads. Journal of Marriage and Family, 38, 15–28. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib68">Strang, J. F., Meagher, H., Kenworthy, L., de Vries, A. L., Menvielle, E., Leibowitz, S., Janssen, A., Cohen-Kettenis, P., Shumer, D. E., Edwards-Leeper, L., Pleak, R. R., Spack, N., Karasic, D. H., Schreier, H., Balleur, A., Tishelman, A., Ehrensaft, D., Rodnan, L., Kuschner, E., et al. (2018). Initial clinical guidelines for co-occurring autism spectrum disorder and gender dysphoria or incongruence in adolescents. Journal of Clinical Child &amp; Adolescent Psychology, 47(1), 105–115. Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib69">Symonds, T., Perelman, M. A., Althof, S., Giuliano, F., Martin, M., May, K., Abraham, L., Crossland, A., &amp; Morris, M. (2007). Development and validation of a premature ejaculation diagnostic tool. European Urology, 52(2), 565–573. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib70">Tordoff, D. M., Wanta, J. W., Collin, A., Stepney, C., Inwards-Breland, D. J., &amp; Ahrens, K. (2022). Mental health outcomes in transgender and nonbinary youths receiving gender-affirming care. JAMA Network Open, 5(2), e220978. CrossrefPubMedPubMedCentral</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib71">van Anders, S. (2015). Beyond sexual orientation: Integrating gender/sex and diverse sexualities via Sexual Configurations Theory. Archives of Sexual Behavior, 44(5), 1177–1213. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib72">VanSlyke, R. (2018). Profile patterns of sex offenders using the Minnesota multiphasic personality inventory–restructured form (MMPI-2-RF). Florida Institute of Technology Scholarship Repository.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib73">Profile patterns of sex offenders using the Minnesota multiphasic personality inventory–restructured form (MMPI-2-RF)https://​repository.​fit.​edu/​cgi/​viewcontent.​cgi?​article=​1374&amp;​context=​etd</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib74">Wilson, R. J., &amp; Miner, M. H. (2016). Measurement of male sexual arousal and interest using penile plethysmography and viewing time. In D. R. Laws &amp; W. O’Donohue (Eds.), Treatment of sex offenders (pp. 107–131). Springer.Crossref</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib75">Wincze, J. P., &amp; Carey, M. P. (2015). Sexual dysfunction: A guide for assessment and treatment. Guilford Publications.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib76">Witte, T. D., Di Placido, C., Gu, D., &amp; Wong, S. C. P. (2006). An investigation of the validity and reliability of the criminal sentiments scale in a sample of treated sex offenders. Sexual Abuse: A Journal of Research and Treatment, 18, 249–258. CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0016s0008bib77">Sexual Abuse: A Journal of Research and Treatment, 18https://​doi.​org/​10.​1177/​1079063206018003​03 CrossrefPubMed</bibliomixed>
   </bibliography>
</sect1>