<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="ch0016s0007" role="Heading">
   <sect1info>
      <risinfo>
         <risprev>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0006</risprev>
         <riscurrent>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0007</riscurrent>
         <risnext>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0008</risnext>
         <booktitle>Diagnostic Interviewing</booktitle>
         <isbn>9781071643624</isbn>
         <chapternumber>16</chapternumber>
         <chapterid>ch0016</chapterid>
         <chaptertitle>14. Sexual Dysfunctions, Gender Dysphoria, and Paraphilic Disorders</chaptertitle>
         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <personname>
                  <firstname>Daniel L.</firstname>
                  <surname>Segal</surname>
               </personname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <publisher>
            <publishername>Springer US</publishername>
         </publisher>
         <pubdate>2025</pubdate>
      </risinfo>
      <primaryauthor>
         <personname>
            <firstname>Daniel L.</firstname>
            <surname>Segal</surname>
         </personname>
      </primaryauthor>
   </sect1info>
   <title>Dos and Don’ts</title>
   <sect2 id="ch0016s0007s01" role="Heading">
      <title>Dos</title>
      <itemizedlist mark="none" role="none">
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">Ask about sexual problems<indexterm significance="normal">
                  <primary>problems</primary>
               </indexterm> in a direct manner no matter what the presenting complaint.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">Be open and nonjudgmental.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">Recognize diversity in all aspects of sexual and gender identity.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">Understand and respect the clients’ religious and cultural beliefs.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">Provide normalizing statements and gently correct misinformation.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">Ask about solitary sexual activities in addition to partnered activities.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">Obtain information about fantasies as they may provide additional insight into the presenting complaints.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">Ask questions about activities (e. g., anal sex) that are important for sexual health.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">Ask about partner communication and the partner’s responses to the presenting complaint.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">If working with a sex offender, gain information from as many sources as possible in order to obtain as comprehensive a history as possible.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">Refer to a medical doctor for physical<indexterm significance="normal">
                  <primary>physical</primary>
               </indexterm>tests, laboratory investigations, and treatment.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">If the individual is partnered, encourage the participation of partner(s) in assessment and treatment.</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="ch0016s0007s02" role="Heading">
      <title>Don’ts</title>
      <itemizedlist mark="none" role="none">
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">Don’t let lack of experience or discomfort with sexual issues prevent you from at least asking some screening questions about sexual dysfunctions; open the door for the client to discuss this topic and see if a referral may be needed if you do not feel competent. Most people will not spontaneously bring up a sexual problem. Direct questions must be asked.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">Don’t assume that you know everything about the client and their fantasies, sexual orientation, relationship status, sexual experiences, gender identity, etc.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">Don’t assume that sex and gender are binary concepts.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">Don’t assume that older people, single people, disabled people, etc., are not sexual or sexually active.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para role="Para">In the case of sex offenders or individuals convicted of sexual crimes, don’t believe everything they tell you as they may want to mislead the clinician into thinking that they are<indexterm significance="normal">
                  <primary>are</primary>
               </indexterm> functioning at higher or lower levels depending on the situation.</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
   </sect2>
</sect1>