<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="ch0016s0001" role="Heading">
   <sect1info>
      <risinfo>
         <risprev>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0009</risprev>
         <riscurrent>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0001</riscurrent>
         <risnext>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0002</risnext>
         <booktitle>Diagnostic Interviewing</booktitle>
         <isbn>9781071643624</isbn>
         <chapternumber>16</chapternumber>
         <chapterid>ch0016</chapterid>
         <chaptertitle>14. Sexual Dysfunctions, Gender Dysphoria, and Paraphilic Disorders</chaptertitle>
         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <personname>
                  <firstname>Daniel L.</firstname>
                  <surname>Segal</surname>
               </personname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <publisher>
            <publishername>Springer US</publishername>
         </publisher>
         <pubdate>2025</pubdate>
      </risinfo>
      <primaryauthor>
         <personname>
            <firstname>Daniel L.</firstname>
            <surname>Segal</surname>
         </personname>
      </primaryauthor>
   </sect1info>
   <title>Description of the Disorders</title>
   <sect2 id="ch0016s0001s01" role="Heading">
      <title>Sexual Dysfunctions</title>
      <para role="Para">
         According<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>According</primary>
         </indexterm> to the DSM-5-TR (American Psychiatric Association, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>), sexual dysfunctions are characterized by disturbances in a person’s ability to respond sexually or to experience sexual pleasure. Sexual dysfunctions consist of clinically significant issues with desire, interest, and arousal (e. g., erection), orgasm (including ejaculation), and genitopelvic pain and penetration, and they may be diagnosed<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>diagnosed</primary>
         </indexterm> as being due to the use of medications and/or substances. When more than one sexual dysfunction is present, all should be recorded (American Psychiatric Association, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). If the presence of a sexual dysfunction can be explained by comorbid nonsexual mental disorders, such as an anxiety or mood disorder, only the nonsexual disorder diagnosis (e. g., generalized anxiety) should be made (American Psychiatric Association,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). In addition, the diagnosis of a sexual dysfunction requires ruling out sexual issues that are better explained by the effects of a medical condition or by severe relationship distress, partner violence, or other stressors (American Psychiatric Association, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>).<phrase>14.1</phrase>
         <phrase>2022</phrase>onsetcontextdistress severityonsetcontext<phrase>2022</phrase>
         <phrase>2021</phrase>Table 14.1</para>
      designations<indexterm significance="normal">
         <primary>designations</primary>
      </indexterm>
      Distress severity<indexterm significance="normal">
         <primary>Distress severity</primary>
      </indexterm>
      clinical<indexterm significance="normal">
         <primary>clinical</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para role="SimplePara">DSM-5-TR sexual<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>sexual</primary>
         </indexterm>dysfunctions according to sex assigned at birth</para>
      <table id="ch0016s0001ta01">
         <title/>
         <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
            <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
            <tbody>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Sexual response cycle phase affected</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Males</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Females</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Desire/interest</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Hypoactive sexual desire disorder</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry morerows="1">
                     <para role="SimplePara">Sexual interest/arousal disorder</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Excitement/arousal</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Erectile disorder</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Orgasm</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Delayed ejaculation</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Premature (early) ejaculation</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Orgasmic disorder</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry/>
                  <entry/>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Genitopelvic pain/penetration disorder</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
            </tbody>
         </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para role="Para">Although not explicitly stated in the DSM-5-TR (but stated in some previous versions), sexual dysfunctions are based on the first three stages<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>stages</primary>
         </indexterm> of the four-phase sexual response cycle (Masters &amp; Johnson, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>1966</phrase>
         </emphasis>): (1) desire/interest, which consists of fantasies about and the wish to engage in sexual activity; (2) excitement/arousal, which manifests as a subjective sexual pleasure and associated physiological changes (e. g., genital lubrication and engorgement); and (3) orgasm, which consists of the release of sexual tension and the rhythmic contractions of genitopelvic muscles and organs. A problem at any one stage of the sexual response cycle is likely to lead to difficulties with other stages; indeed, clinically, a high comorbidity among the sexual dysfunctions is observed. For example, a client presenting with orgasm difficulties may also experience problems with desire/interest. In addition, genitopelvic pain can potentially interfere with any or all aspects of sexual response. Although sound empirical data on comorbidities are lacking, a recent consensus paper concluded that comorbidity among sexual dysfunctions was more common among cis women than cis men (Mc Cabe et al.,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>).</para>
      <para role="Para">Although the DSM-5-TR has continued a long<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>long</primary>
         </indexterm> tradition that separates sexual dysfunctions into those that affect cis men and cis women—with some of them named in a gender/sex-specific manner<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>manner</primary>
         </indexterm>(e. g., male hypoactive sexual desire disorder, female sexual interest/arousal disorder)—it specifies that the diagnostic criteria can be applied to people of any gender/sex given that they describe symptoms that are not gender/sex-dependent (American Psychiatric Association,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). Furthermore, it specifies that any diagnosis referring to anatomy (e. g., genitopelvic pain/penetration disorder refers to, for example, vaginal penetration and vulvovaginal pain) should be based on the client’s current anatomy and not on their sex assigned at birth (American Psychiatric Association,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). Clinical judgment will play an important role in ensuring appropriate, relevant diagnoses are made for gender minority clients (individuals who are, for example, trans or non-binary), especially since research on sexual dysfunctions in this population is limited.</para>
      <para role="Para">Sexual desire and arousal disorders include male hypoactive sexual desire disorder (HSDD)<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>hypoactive sexual desire disorder (HSDD)</primary>
         </indexterm>, erectile disorder (ED)<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>erectile disorder (ED)</primary>
         </indexterm>, and female sexual interest/arousal disorder (SIAD)<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>sexual interest/arousal disorder (SIAD)</primary>
         </indexterm>. The diagnosis of male HSDD<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>HSDD</primary>
         </indexterm> is made when a client describes persistent or recurrent deficient (or absent) sexual/erotic thoughts or fantasies and desire for sexual activity (American Psychiatric Association, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). Although the DSM-5 considers desire dysfunctions as distinct from arousal dysfunctions for men (i. e., there are separate diagnoses for HSDD and ED; Table<emphasis role="InternalRef">
            <phrase>14.1</phrase>
         </emphasis>), this distinction is not made for women. Based on research indicating that women recognize a high degree of overlap in perceptions of sexual desire and arousal (Graham et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2004</phrase>
         </emphasis>, this pattern is also true of men; Janssen et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2008</phrase>
         </emphasis>), the DSM-5-TR includes the diagnosis of SIAD, which replaced the former diagnoses of female HSDD and female sexual arousal disorder (FSAD). SIAD is characterized by at least three of the following: absent/reduced (1) interest in sexual activity; (2) sexual/erotic thoughts or fantasies; (3) sexual excitement/pleasure during<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>during</primary>
         </indexterm>sexual activity<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>activity</primary>
         </indexterm> in almost all or all (75–100%) sexual encounters; (4) sexual interest/arousal in<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>in</primary>
         </indexterm> response to any internal or external sexual/erotic cues; and (5) genital/nongenital sensations during sexual activity (75–100% of encounters); and no/reduced initiation of sexual activity<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>activity</primary>
         </indexterm> and typically unreceptive to a partner’s attempts to initiate (American Psychiatric Association, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). The prevalence of desire disorders in women is estimated to be between 15 and 55%—with rates of 40–50% in those aged 65 years and above—and between 15 and 25% in men (Mc Cabe et al.,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>). A diagnosis of ED is made when at least one of the following three symptoms are experienced on all or almost all (75–100%) sexual encounters: marked difficulty in <emphasis>obtaining</emphasis> or <emphasis>maintaining</emphasis> an erection, or a marked <emphasis>decrease in erectile rigidity</emphasis> (American Psychiatric Association, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). A wide range of prevalence rates is reported<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>reported</primary>
         </indexterm>for ED<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>ED</primary>
         </indexterm>(i. e., 15–76%) as rates vary with age; overall, the prevalence<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>prevalence</primary>
         </indexterm>rate of ED in the USA is 22% (Mc Cabe et al.,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>).</para>
      <para role="Para">Orgasmic disorders consist of female orgasmic disorder (FOD)<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>female orgasmic disorder (FOD)</primary>
         </indexterm>, and, in men, delayed ejaculation (DE)<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>delayed ejaculation (DE)</primary>
         </indexterm> and premature (early) ejaculation (PE)<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>premature (early) ejaculation (PE)</primary>
         </indexterm>. FOD<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>FOD</primary>
         </indexterm> is characterized by the presence of at least one of the following symptoms (experienced in 75–100% of sexual encounters): marked delay in, marked infrequency<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>infrequency</primary>
         </indexterm>of, or absence of orgasm; and markedly reduced intensity of orgasmic sensations (American Psychiatric Association, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). FOD is estimated to affect between 16 and 25% of women (Mc Cabe et al.,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>). The diagnostic criteria for DE<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>DE</primary>
         </indexterm> consist of at least one of the following symptoms (experienced in 75–100% of sexual encounters), without desiring the delay: marked delay in ejaculation, and marked infrequency or absence of ejaculation (American Psychiatric Association, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). The prevalence of DE is 1–10% (Mc Cabe et al.,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>). PE, which affects approximately 8–30% of men of all ages (Mc Cabe et al.,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>), is diagnosed when a patient describes a persistent or recurrent pattern of ejaculation experienced in 75–100% of partnered sexual encounters within approximately one minute following vaginal penetration and before the individual wishes it. Note that these criteria can also be applied to nonvaginal penetration activities; however, specific<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>specific</primary>
         </indexterm>duration criteria have not yet been established for these activities (American Psychiatric Association, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>).</para>
      <para role="Para">
         Genitopelvic pain/penetration disorder (GPPPD)<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>Genitopelvic pain/penetration disorder (GPPPD)</primary>
         </indexterm> is a sexual<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>sexual</primary>
         </indexterm>dysfunction that is currently restricted to individuals with female-typical genitopelvic anatomy; it affects between 14 and 27% of women (Mc Cabe et al.,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>). The diagnosis of GPPPD involves persistent or recurrent difficulties with at least one of the following: (1) vaginal penetration during intercourse; (2) marked vulvovaginal/pelvic pain during vaginal intercourse or penetration attempts; (3) marked fear/anxiety about vulvovaginal/pelvic pain in anticipation of, during, or as a result of vaginal penetration; and (4) marked tensing or tightening of the pelvic floor muscles during attempted vaginal penetration (American Psychiatric Association, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). Despite a large representation of research on genitopelvic pain in men<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>men</primary>
         </indexterm>and an estimated prevalence of 16.8% (Mc Cabe et al.,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>), the DSM-5-TR states that new research on genitopelvic pain in men suggests that a similar dysfunction may be diagnosable in the future. In the meantime, the DSM-5-TR suggests using the diagnoses of an “other specified” or an “unspecified” sexual dysfunction for men with<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>with</primary>
         </indexterm> genitopelvic pain.</para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="ch0016s0001s02" role="Heading">
      <title>Gender Dysphoria</title>
      Gender dysphoria (GD)<indexterm significance="normal">
         <primary>Gender dysphoria (GD)</primary>
      </indexterm>
      the<indexterm significance="normal">
         <primary>the</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
         <phrase>2018</phrase>
         <phrase>2022</phrase>
         <phrase>2022</phrase>
         <phrase>2018</phrase>
         <phrase>14.2</phrase>
         <phrase>2022</phrase>Table 14.2</para>
      clinical guidelines<indexterm significance="normal">
         <primary>clinical guidelines</primary>
      </indexterm>
      separate<indexterm significance="normal">
         <primary>separate</primary>
      </indexterm>
      dysphoria<indexterm significance="normal">
         <primary>dysphoria</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para role="SimplePara">
         Diagnostic features<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>Diagnostic features</primary>
         </indexterm> for gender dysphoria in children and adolescents/adults</para>
      <table id="ch0016s0001ta02">
         <title/>
         <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
            <tbody>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Gender dysphoria in children</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Gender dysphoria in adolescents and adults</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">At least six of the following (including the first one, which is<emphasis>required</emphasis> for diagnosis)</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">1. A strong desire to be of the other gender or an insistence that one is the other gender (or a different gender from one’s assigned gender)</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">2. In boys (assigned gender), a strong preference for cross-dressing or simulating female apparel; or in girls (assigned gender), a strong preference for wearing only typical masculine attire and a strong resistance to the wearing of typical feminine clothing</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">3. A strong preference for cross-gender roles in make-believe/fantasy play</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">4. A strong preference for the toys, games, or activities stereotypically used or engaged in by the other gender</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">5. A strong preference for playmates of the other gender</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">6. In boys (assigned gender), a strong rejection of typically masculine toys, games, and activities and a strong avoidance of rough-and-tumble play; or in girls (assigned gender), a strong rejection of typically feminine toys, games, and activities</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">7. A strong dislike of one’s sexual anatomy</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">8. A strong desire for the primary and/or secondary sex characteristics that match one’s experienced gender</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">At least two of the following</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">1. A marked incongruence between one’s experienced/expressed gender and primary and/or secondary sex characteristics (or in young adolescents, the anticipated secondary sex characteristics)</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">2. A strong desire to be rid of one’s primary and/or secondary sex characteristics because of a marked incongruence with one’s experienced/expressed gender (or in young adolescents, a desire to prevent the development of the anticipated secondary sex characteristics)</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">3. A strong desire for the primary and/or secondary sex characteristics of the other gender</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">4. A strong desire to be of the other gender (or a different gender from one’s assigned gender)</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">5. A strong desire to be treated as the other gender (or a different gender from one’s assigned gender)</para>
                     <para role="SimplePara">6. A strong conviction that one has the typical feelings and reactions of the other gender (or a different gender from one’s assigned gender)</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
            </tbody>
         </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para role="SimplePara">Note: Adapted from DSM-5-TR</para>
      <para role="Para">It is important to be aware of the high levels of vulnerability<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>vulnerability</primary>
         </indexterm> of people with GD: before gender-affirming care, they are at increased risk for a variety of mental health disorders including depression and anxiety, and are at increased risk of suicidality (Tordoff et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). These symptoms remit for most individuals once they undergo gender-affirming care (Tordoff et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>) and interventions that lessen discriminatory and minority stress (Bauer et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2015</phrase>
         </emphasis>). Gender affirmation consists of a variety of options, some nonmedical (e. g., social and legal transition) and some medical (e. g., hormonal treatment, surgery) (Coleman et al.,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). Not all individuals with GD will undergo gender-affirming surgery or hormone therapy, and not all will seek mental health care (Margulies et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2021</phrase>
         </emphasis>).</para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="ch0016s0001s03" role="Heading">
      <title>Paraphilic Disorders</title>
      <para>
         <phrase>2022</phrase>
         <phrase>2022</phrase>paraphiliaparaphilic disorder<phrase>14.3</phrase>Table 14.3</para>
      defines<indexterm significance="normal">
         <primary>defines</primary>
      </indexterm>
      than<indexterm significance="normal">
         <primary>than</primary>
      </indexterm>
      are<indexterm significance="normal">
         <primary>are</primary>
      </indexterm>
      disorder<indexterm significance="normal">
         <primary>disorder</primary>
      </indexterm>
      DSM-5-TR<indexterm significance="normal">
         <primary>DSM-5-TR</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para role="SimplePara">The DSM-5-TR paraphilic disorders</para>
      <table id="ch0016s0001ta03">
         <title/>
         <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
            <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
            <tbody>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Paraphilic disorders</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Criterion A (and other relevant information), as manifested by fantasies, urges, or behaviors. Recurrent and intense sexual arousal from…</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Criterion B</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Voyeuristic disorder</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">…observing an unsuspecting person (who is at least 18 years of age) who is naked, in the process of undressing, or engaging in sexual activity</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry morerows="3">
                     <para role="SimplePara">The individual has acted on these sexual urges with a nonconsenting person, or the sexual urges or fantasies cause clinically significant distress or impairment in social, occupational, or other important areas of functioning</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Exhibitionistic disorder</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">…the exposure of one’s genitals to an unsuspecting person</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Frotteuristic disorder</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">…touching or rubbing against a nonconsenting person</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Sexual sadism disorder</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">…the physical or psychological suffering of another person</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Sexual masochism disorder</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">…the act of being humiliated, beaten, bound, or otherwise made to suffer</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry morerows="2">
                     <para role="SimplePara">The fantasies, sexual urges, or behaviors cause clinically significant distress or impairment in social, occupational, or other important areas of functioning</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Fetishistic disorder</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">…either the use of nonliving objects or a highly specific focus on non-genital body part(s)</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Transvestic disorder</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">…cross-dressing</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Pedophilic disorder</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">Recurrent, intense sexually arousing fantasies, sexual urges, or behaviors involving sexual activity with a prepubescent child or children (generally age 13 years or younger)<superscript>a</superscript>
                     </para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     <para role="SimplePara">The individual has acted on these sexual urges, or the sexual urges or fantasies cause marked distress or interpersonal difficulty</para>
                  </entry>
               </row>
            </tbody>
         </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para role="SimplePara">
         <superscript>a</superscript> The individual must be at least 16 years old and at least 5 years older than the child/children; must not include an individual in late adolescence involved in an ongoing sexual relationship with a 12- or 13-year-old</para>
      <para role="Para">In terms of the course<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>course</primary>
         </indexterm>specifiers, both the terms “in full remission” and “in a controlled environment” can generally be applied to paraphilic disorders. An exception is that pedophilic disorders cannot be declared to be in remission, which has fostered some debate (e. g., Briken et al.,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2014</phrase>
         </emphasis>). These specifiers were incorporated to reflect the potential for a person to greatly reduce the likelihood of acting on paraphilic interests, thereby countervailing distress, impairment, and the potential for harm. Under such conditions, the paraphilia remains but the paraphilic disorder is deemed to be in remission. The specifier regarding the presence of a controlled environment was included because many individuals who have acted on paraphilic interests<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>interests</primary>
         </indexterm> have restrictions on their liberty, thereby rendering it difficult to assess their ongoing tendencies.</para>
      <para role="Para">With regard to the prevalence<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>prevalence</primary>
         </indexterm> of paraphilic disorders, the DSM-5-TR cautions that there is considerable uncertainty. It is estimated<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>estimated</primary>
         </indexterm> that the percentage of men who have acted on such paraphilic impulses is (at most) 12% for voyeuristic disorder, 2–4% for exhibitionistic disorder, 10–14% for frotteuristic disorder, and around 3–5% for pedophilic disorder (American Psychiatric Association, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). All rates are higher for men than women and sometimes substantially so. The reasons for this disparity are unclear, although sexual drive has been proposed as a mediator (Dawson et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>) and there is some suggestion that rates are somewhat higher for women than previously reported (Joyal &amp; Carpentier, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2017</phrase>
         </emphasis>).</para>
   </sect2>
</sect1>