<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="ch0016s0002" role="Heading">
   <sect1info>
      <risinfo>
         <risprev>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0001</risprev>
         <riscurrent>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0002</riscurrent>
         <risnext>sect1.9781071643624.ch0016s0003</risnext>
         <booktitle>Diagnostic Interviewing</booktitle>
         <isbn>9781071643624</isbn>
         <chapternumber>16</chapternumber>
         <chapterid>ch0016</chapterid>
         <chaptertitle>14. Sexual Dysfunctions, Gender Dysphoria, and Paraphilic Disorders</chaptertitle>
         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <personname>
                  <firstname>Daniel L.</firstname>
                  <surname>Segal</surname>
               </personname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <publisher>
            <publishername>Springer US</publishername>
         </publisher>
         <pubdate>2025</pubdate>
      </risinfo>
      <primaryauthor>
         <personname>
            <firstname>Daniel L.</firstname>
            <surname>Segal</surname>
         </personname>
      </primaryauthor>
   </sect1info>
   <title>Procedures for Gathering Information</title>
   <sect2 id="ch0016s0002s01" role="Heading">
      <title>Sexual Dysfunctions</title>
      <para role="Para">The clinical interview<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>clinical interview</primary>
         </indexterm>is the main technique with which to assess and diagnose sexual dysfunctions. There is no widely used, validated, standardized interview for sexual dysfunctions as is the case for many other DSM-5-TR disorders. However, several authors have proposed clinical interview guidelines and recommendations for coverage of topics and processes (e. g., Levine et al.,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>; Wincze &amp; Carey, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2015</phrase>
         </emphasis>).</para>
      <para role="Para">The clinical interview typically starts with the individual describing the nature of the problem and the reason for seeking treatment. Following an open-ended description of the problem, the clinician may ask more specific questions about when the problem started (onset), the conditions under which it<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>it</primary>
         </indexterm>occurs (context), and the extent of the problem and amount of distress experienced because<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>because</primary>
         </indexterm>of the issue (severity). Questions can then be asked about the various biological, psychological, and social problems that might be implicated (Levine et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>; Wincze &amp; Carey, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2015</phrase>
         </emphasis>). In terms of general biological factors, the clinician should assess and take into account age, general health status (e. g., body mass index), lifestyle factors (e. g., diet, cigarette smoking), hormone levels, chronic pain syndromes (e. g., chronic prostatitis syndrome, vulvodynia), hormone levels, and medical illnesses that affect vascular, sensory, central, and nervous system functions. In addition, questions regarding past surgeries and injuries, especially those in the genital or pelvic region, and past and current medications should be posed (Levine et al.,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>; Wincze &amp; Carey, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2015</phrase>
         </emphasis>). It is commonly understood that many medications, such as antidepressants, antipsychotics, and antihypertensives<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>antihypertensives</primary>
         </indexterm>, can detrimentally affect sexual functioning (Healy et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>).</para>
      <para role="Para">With respect to individual psychological factors, depression and anxiety<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>psychological factors, depression and anxiety</primary>
         </indexterm> are often comorbid with sexual dysfunction. If present and treatment does not target the associated mood disorders, treatment will likely not be successful. Substance abuse disorders<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>Substance abuse disorders</primary>
         </indexterm> may also have a major negative impact on sexual functioning. Certain maladaptive cognitive sets, unrealistic expectations, misinformation or lack of information, and negative emotional reactions can also impinge upon sexual function. Past sexual trauma and other negative experiences may set the foundation for sexual<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>sexual</primary>
         </indexterm>problems as well (Levine et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>; Wincze &amp; Carey, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2015</phrase>
         </emphasis>). Socially, family-of-origin attitudes regarding sexuality may be instilled early on and predispose the development of a sexual dysfunction. Assessing the quality of the individual’s current relationship is of utmost importance, as problems between the members of the couple may be a cause and/or a consequence of sexual problems. If so, these issues need to be appropriately addressed. Areas of inquiry related to intimate partnership should include anger, distrust, discrepancies in sexual drive, and preferences, communication, and physical attraction (Levine et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>; Wincze &amp; Carey, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2015</phrase>
         </emphasis>). The comorbidity<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>comorbidity</primary>
         </indexterm> of partner sexual dysfunction is common and should be assessed and addressed if the partner(s) is/are willing to be present in the sessions. In addition, ethnocultural and religious attitudes and beliefs are important as they can be implicated in the development and maintenance of sexual dysfunctions (Hall &amp; Graham, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2013</phrase>
         </emphasis>; Levine et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2016</phrase>
         </emphasis>; Wincze &amp; Carey, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2015</phrase>
         </emphasis>).</para>
      <para role="Para">
         Questionnaires<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>Questionnaires</primary>
         </indexterm>can be used to formally assess the presence and/or comorbidity of sexual dysfunctions. In addition, information from the client’s treating physician with respect to results from laboratory tests (e. g., for hormone function, vascular integrity, nerve function) and physical<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>physical</primary>
         </indexterm>examinations (e. g., gynecological) will provide useful information for diagnosis and treatment.</para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="ch0016s0002s02" role="Heading">
      <title>Gender Dysphoria</title>
      <para role="Para">The most<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>most</primary>
         </indexterm> recent guideline for the Standards of Care for Gender Diverse People—published by the World Professional Association for Transgender Health (WPATH) in 2022 (Coleman et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>) and freely available at <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
            <ulink url="http://www.wpath.org/">
               <emphasis role="RefSource">www.​wpath.​org/​</emphasis>
            </ulink>
         </emphasis>—makes several recommendations for healthcare professionals involved in the care of gender diverse individuals and outlines the process of mental health assessment of individuals with GD. The recommendations for healthcare professionals<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>professionals</primary>
         </indexterm> involved in the care of gender diverse adults are that they be: licensed by their statutory board with relevant training; competent in diagnosing mental health disorders preferably using the most recent edition of the World Health Organization’s International Classification of Diseases (or another taxonomy); able to identify co-existing mental health and other psychosocial issues and distinguish these from GD, incongruence, and diversity; capable of assessing capacity to consent to treatment; experienced or qualified to assess clinical aspects of GD, incongruence, and diversity; continuing their education in health care related to GD, incongruence, and diversity; and open to multidisciplinary consultation and referral with other health care professionals involved<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>involved</primary>
         </indexterm> in gender-affirming care (Coleman et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). Additional recommendations are made for mental health care professionals<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>health care professionals</primary>
         </indexterm>involved in gender-affirming medical and surgical treatment of children and adolescents with GD as well as with other gender-diverse individuals seeking care (e. g., eunuchs) (Coleman et al.,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>).</para>
      <para role="Para">The role of mental health professionals<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>professionals</primary>
         </indexterm> involved in the care of gender diverse individuals consists of many aspects related to the overall well-being of their clients as well as the implementation of specific recommendations when discussing avenues of gender-affirming medical care. Mental health professionals play a critical role in multidisciplinary healthcare teams by conducting a comprehensive assessment to diagnose GD and addressing mental health symptoms that interfere with a client’s capacity to consent to gender-affirming care. Examples of interfering symptoms are cognitive impairment and the presence of psychosis; it is also important to understand that some mental health conditions may not affect the capacity to provide consent and should not be used as a reason to delay gender-affirming care, especially since such care is associated with decreases in mental health symptoms (Coleman et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). In addition, mental health professionals address mental health conditions that can interfere with a client’s capacity to engage in essential perioperative care. For example, substance use disorder may impede engagement with appointments, and providing treatment for this condition and support for the client will be necessary for positive surgical outcomes (Coleman et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>). Additional<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>Additional</primary>
         </indexterm>
         recommendations<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>recommendations</primary>
         </indexterm> specific to mental health professionals can be found in the Standards of Care (Coleman et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2022</phrase>
         </emphasis>).</para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="ch0016s0002s03" role="Heading">
      <title>Paraphilic Disorders</title>
      <para role="Para">This section will focus on the assessment procedures of adult men with paraphilic disorders. Very few women are identified with paraphilias, especially in forensic populations (for a review, see Cortoni,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2018</phrase>
         </emphasis>); in addition, paraphilic disorders are generally not diagnosed in adolescence given that this period of sexual development is believed to be exploratory and fluid, and a premature diagnosis of a paraphilic disorder could pathologize sexual behavior that is within a normal range developmentally (Seto, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2018</phrase>
         </emphasis>).</para>
      <para role="Para">Certain paraphilias and their associated disorders are more likely to be encountered in a forensic setting<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>forensic setting</primary>
         </indexterm>(e. g., pedophilic disorder), and others are more common in traditional mental health settings (e. g., fetishistic disorder). In either case, the approach to the assessment will be similar, although a forensic setting is likely to be more concerned with broader issues such as risk to the public. In addition, those undergoing court assessments may be less inclined to be forthright than those seeking assessment of their own volition. Regardless, the assessment should be facilitated by a warm, respectful, empathic, genuine, and supportive demeanor on the part of the interviewer (Wilcox &amp; Gray,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2017</phrase>
         </emphasis>). The Association for the Treatment of Sexual Abusers (ATSA; <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
            <ulink url="http://www.atsa.com/">
               <emphasis role="RefSource">http://​www.​atsa.​com/​</emphasis>
            </ulink>
         </emphasis>) offers practice guidelines<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>guidelines</primary>
         </indexterm> for psychosexual evaluations, and these guidelines emphasize the need to use<indexterm significance="normal">
            <primary>use</primary>
         </indexterm> multiple sources of information, especially when the assessment is involuntary. Interviews should promote engagement, incorporate the client’s perspective, and consider responsivity factors, which refer to individual characteristics and learning differences that may impact treatment effectiveness. Assessors are encouraged to gather information that includes, but is not limited to, the following: psychosexual development; the nature and frequency of sexual practices; paraphilic interests that may not be sexually abusive; the use of sexually oriented services or outlets (including pornography); abusive or offense-related sexual arousal, interests, and preferences; the history of sexually abusive behaviors; information about current and/or previous victim(s); contextual elements of sexually abusive behaviors; and the individual’s level of insight, self-disclosure, and denial (Association for the Treatment of Sexual Abusers, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
            <phrase>2014</phrase>
         </emphasis>, pp. 18–21).</para>
   </sect2>
</sect1>